JOHN EINSET

Professor Emeritus (Plant Physiology) Norwegian University of Life Sciences 1432 Ås, Norway

Summary: has more than 40 years experience in research in the area of plant physiology; initially related to plant hormone analysis and physiological effect studies, subsequently using molecular methods for studies of plant physiology. Academic career plus worked 5 years as Senior Scientist in a plant biotechnology company in USA. During the last 10 years, has focused on functional genomic approaches using the Arabidopsis model system to identify genes affecting stress (low temperature, ionizing radiation) tolerance/sensitivity with current interests directed towards understanding thresholds and mechanisms involved in DNA damage and repair after low-dose radiation exposures.

Education:

Cornell University, 1969
University of Wisconsin, 1974
University of Wisconsin, 1974-1977
Bachelor of Science, with Distinction
Ph.D. (botany)
Research Associate (botany)

Positions held:

University of California-Riverside	1977-1983
Assistant/Associate Professor (plant physiology)	
Harvard University/Arnold Arboretum	1983-1987
Associate Professor (botany, plant physiology)	
EniChem Americas (Biotech Laboratory was closed 12/31/90)	1987-1990
Senior Scientist in plant biotechnology	
Lambertville Tomato Factory (greenhouse tomato business)	1991-1992
Owner and Operator	
Educational Testing Service	1992-1993
Associate Examiner (biochemistry, cell & molecular biology)	
Bucks County Community College	1992-1993
Instructor (human anatomy and physiology)	1992-1993
Norwegian University of Life Sciences	1993-
Research Scientist	
Professor (plant physiology)	1998-2013
Professor Emeritus	2013-

Recent publications:

J. Einset and A. R. Collins 2015 DNA repair after X-irradiation: lessons from plants. Mutagenesis 30: 45-50

Journal: Environmental Research

Title: Salt tolerance of native vegetation collected from the Ethiopian Rift Valley

Lake areas. Corresponding Author: Yetneberk Kassaye

Co-Authors: Brit Salbu, Lindis Skipperud, Sondre Meland, John Einset

- Y.A. Kassaye, B. Salbu, L. Skipperud and J. Einset 2013 High tolerance of aluminum in the grass species Cynodon aethiopicus. Acta Physiol Plant 35 (6): 1749-1761
- Y. A. Kassaye, L. Skipperud, S. Meland, E. Dadebo, J. Einset and B. Salbu 2012 Trace element mobility and transfer to vegetation within the Ethiopian Rift Valley lake areas. J. Environ. Monit. 14: 2698–2709
- E. Farmen, H.N. Mikkelsen, Ø. Evensen, J. Einset, L.S. Heier, B.O. Rosseland, B. Salbu, K.E. Tollefsen and D.H. Oughton 2011 Acute and sub-lethal effects in juvenile Atlantic salmon exposed to low concentrations of Ag nanoparticles. Aquatic Toxicology 108: 78–84
- J. Einset 2011 Transcriptomics Identifies Cold Stress Determinants in Arabidopsis. Bentham Publishers, USA ISBN: No.: 978-1-60805-058-1; pp. 76-81. (peer reviewed)
- J. Einset 2010 Gene Discovery for Chilling Stress Determinants in *Arabidopsis*. Acta Hort., 867: 107-111.
- J. Einset 2009 Chemical Genetics Identifies New Chilling Stress Determinants in Arabidopsis. In: Plant cold hardiness: from the laboratory to the field. Edited by L. Gusta, M. Wisniewski and K. Tanino CABI Publishers, pp. 262-268.
- J. Einset and E. L. Connolly 2009 Glycine betaine enhances extracellular processes blocking ROS signaling during stress. Plant Signaling & Behaviour 4: 197-199
- Einset, J. and B. Salbu 2008 Responses to free radical induction in vegetation Arabidopsis as reference model. International Conference on Radioecology and Environmental Radiation, Bergen, Norway, 16-20 June 2008 (Extended Abstract with Referee)
- J. Einset, Winge, P., Bones, A. and E. L. Connolly 2008 The FRO2 Ferric Reductase is Required for Glycine Betaine's Effect on Chilling Tolerance in Arabidopsis Roots. Physiol. Plant. 134: 334-341
- J. Einset, E. Nielsen, E. L. Connolly, A. Bones, T. Sparstad, P. Winge and J.-K. Zhu 2007 Membrane Trafficking RabA4c Involved in the Effect of Glycine Betaine on Recovery from Chilling Stress in Arabidopsis. Physiol. Plant. 130: 511-518
- J. Einset, P. Winge and A. Bones 2007 ROS Signaling Pathways in Chilling Stress. Plant Signaling & Behaviour 2: 5, 365-367